Willian Tessaro Lunardi

Lead Research Scientist at TII

Email: wtlunar@gmail.com | Mobile: +971-55-191-4491 Scholar | LinkedIn | Github | https://wtlunar.com/

SUMMARY

Lead Research Scientist with a Ph.D. in Computer Science from the University of Luxembourg. Specialized in machine learning, deep learning, combinatorial optimization, and out-of-distribution detection. Have a proven track record of developing advanced algorithms and models in both academic and industry settings.

EDUCATION

• University of Luxembourg

Doctor of Philosophy in Computer Science

Luxembourg, Luxembourg 2016 - 2020

• PUC of Rio Grande do Sul

Master of Science in Computer Science

RS, Brazil 2014 – 2016

• University of Passo Fundo

Bachelor of Science in Computer Science

RS, Brazil 2010 – 2014

EXPERIENCE

• Technology Innovation Institute, Lead Researcher

Abu Dhabi, UAE, Jan 2023 - Present

• Technology Innovation Institute, Senior Researcher

Abu Dhabi, UAE, Jun 2021 - Jan 2023

- Developed self-supervised contrastive methods for learning one-class representations for out-of-distribution detection.
- o Developed adversarial training regularization approach for enhancing autoencoder performance for network anomaly detection.
- Developed voice recognition solutions using contrastive learning and raw/spectrograms, improving accuracy on audio datasets.
- University of Luxembourg, Research Associate

Luxembourg, Luxembourg, Jun 2020 – Jun 2021

- o Developed neural combinatorial optimization strategies using graph networks and reinforcement learning.
- Developed an out-of-distribution detection methods for predictive maintenance using autoencoders.
- Developed metaheuristics for vehicle routing, optimizing routing and scheduling with coverage and energy constraints.
- Deployed scheduling and routing algorithms in C++ for a European company, boosting operational efficiency.
- University of Luxembourg, Doctoral Researcher

Luxembourg, Luxembourg, Jun 2016 – Jun 2020

- o Developed MILP and CP models for industrial scheduling, addressing complex availability, overlapping, and setup constraints.
- o Developed novel hybrid neighborhood functions and global metaheuristics, achieving SOTA results in the FJSP problem.
- Developed SOTA optimization algorithms, validated by publications in 10+ international conferences and journals.
- o Collaborated with IBM Paris, implementing models in real-world settings, enhancing production and revenue.

SKILLS

- Programming Languages: Python, C++, Javascript, C#, and Java.
- Frameworks and Libraries: PyTorch, Scikit-learn, SciPy, Numpy, Pandas, Matplotlib, Plotly, Seaborn, Django, among others.
- Database Management: SQL, PostgreSQL, MySQL, ORM such as Hibernate in Java.
- Others: OpenMP, Boost (C++), Unity 3D (C#), p5js (JS), Bootstrap (JS), processing (Java).

Additional Information

- Dual Citizenship: Brazil and Italy.
- Languages: Portuguese (native), English (fluent), Spanish (basic), and Italian (basic).

Research Interests

Machine Learning, Deep Learning, Out-of-Distribution Detection, Anomaly Detection, Optimization, Representation Learning, Generative AI, Self-supervised Learning, Unsupervised Learning, Few-shot Learning, Data Augmentation, Neural Networks.

HIGHLIGHTED PUBLICATIONS

- [2023] W. T. Lunardi, M. A. Lopez, and J.-P. Giacalone, "ARCADE: Adversarially Regularized Convolutional Autoencoder for Network Anomaly Detection," *IEEE Transactions on Network and Service Management, Special Issue on Machine Learning and Artificial Intelligence*, vol. 20, no. 2, pp. 1305–1318, 2023, [URL].
- [2021] W. T. Lunardi, E. G. Birgin, D. P. Ronconi, et al., "Metaheuristics for the Online Printing Shop Scheduling Problem," European Journal of Operational Research, vol. 293, no. 2, pp. 419–441, 2021, [URL].
- [2020] W. T. Lunardi, E. G. Birgin, P. Laborie, et al., "Mixed Integer Linear Programming and Constraint Programming Models for the Online Printing Shop Scheduling Problem," Computers & Operations Research, vol. 123, p. 105 020, 2020, [URL].

- [2023] M. Gallacher, M. A. Sankar, W. T. Lunardi, et al., "Towards speaker identification on resource-constrained embedded devices," in *Proceedings of the ACM Conference on Embedded Networked Sensor Systems*, 2023, [URL].
- [2023] D. Herzalla, W. T. Lunardi, and M. Andreoni, "TII-SSRC-23 Dataset: Typological Exploration of Diverse Traffic Patterns for Intrusion Detection," *IEEE Access*, 2023, [URL].
- [2022] A. R. B. Nabila, E. K. Viegas, and W. T. Lunardi, "A Generative Adversarial Network-based Attack for Audio-based Condition Monitoring Systems," in *Proceedings of the IEEE Consumer Communications & Networking Conference*, 2022, [URL].
- [2022] A. S. Ali, W. T. Lunardi, L. Bariah, et al., "Deep Reinforcement Learning Based Anti-Jamming Using Clear Channel Assessment Information in a Cognitive Radio Environment," in Proceedings of the IEEE International Conference on Advanced Communication Technologies and Networking, 2022, [URL].
- [2022] A. S. Ali, M. Baddeley, L. Bariah, et al., "JamRF: Performance Analysis, Evaluation, and Implementation of RF Jamming Over Wi-Fi," *IEEE Access*, vol. 10, pp. 133 370–133 384, 2022, [URL].
- [2022] A. S. Ali, M. Baddeley, L. Bariah, et al., "Performance Analysis and Evaluation of RF Jamming in IoT Networks," in *Proceedings of the IEEE Global Communications Conference*, 2022, [URL].
- [2021] M. A. Lopez, M. Baddeley, W. T. Lunardi, et al., "Towards Secure Wireless Mesh Networks for UAV Swarm Connectivity: Current Threats, Research, and Opportunities," in Proceedings of the IEEE International Conference on Distributed Computing in Sensor Systems, 2021, [URL].
- [2019] W. T. Lunardi, H. Voos, and L. H. Cherri, "An Effective Hybrid Imperialist Competitive Algorithm and Tabu Search for an Extended Flexible Job Shop Scheduling Problem," in *Proceedings of the ACM Symposium on Applied Computing*, 2019, [URL].
- [2019] H. de Faria Jr, W. T. Lunardi, and H. Voos, "A Parallel Multi-Population Biased Random-Key Genetic Algorithm for Electric Distribution Network Reconfiguration," in *Proceedings of the ACM Genetic and Evolutionary Computation Conference*, 2019, [URL].
- [2018] W. T. Lunardi and H. Voos, "An Extended Flexible Job Shop Scheduling Problem with Parallel Operations," ACM SIGAPP Applied Computing Review, vol. 18, no. 2, pp. 46–56, 2018, [URL].
- [2018] W. T. Lunardi, H. Voos, and L. H. Cherri, "An Imperialist Competitive Algorithm for a Real-World Flexible Job Shop Scheduling Problem," in *Proceedings of the IEEE International Conference on Emerging Technologies & Factory Automation*, 2018, [URL].
- [2018] W. T. Lunardi, L. H. Cherri, and H. Voos, "A Mathematical Model and a Firefly Algorithm for an Extended Flexible Job Shop Problem with Availability Constraints," in *Proceedings of the Springer International Conference on Artificial Intelligence and Soft Computing*, 2018, [URL].
- [2018] W. T. Lunardi and H. Voos, "Comparative Study of Genetic and Discrete Firefly Algorithm for Combinatorial Optimization," in *Proceedings of the ACM Annual Symposium on Applied Computing*, 2018, [URL].
- [2016] W. T. Lunardi, L. Amaral, S. Marczak, et al., "Automated Decision Support IoT Framework," in Proceedings of the IEEE International Conference on Emerging Technologies & Factory Automation, 2016, [URL].
- [2016] L. A. Amaral, E. De Matos, R. T. Tiburski, et al., "Middleware Technology for IoT Systems: Challenges and Perspectives Toward 5G," in *Internet of Things (IoT) in 5G Mobile Technologies*. Springer, 2016, pp. 333–367, [URL].
- [2015] E. de Matos, L. A. Amaral, R. Tiburski, et al., "Context-Aware System for Information Services Provision in the Internet of Things," in Proceedings of the IEEE Conference on Emerging Technologies & Factory Automation, 2015, [URL].
- [2015] E. de Matos, **W. Lunardi**, L. Amaral, et al., "Context-Based Framework for the Discovery, Search, and Selection of Computing Devices in the Internet of Things," in *Proceedings of the SBC Integrated Software and Hardware Seminar*, 2015, [URL].
- [2015] W. T. Lunardi, E. de Matos, R. Tiburski, et al., "Context-Based Search Engine for Industrial IoT: Discovery, Search, Selection, and Usage of Devices," in Proceedings of the IEEE Conference on Emerging Technologies & Factory Automation, 2015, [URL].

Work in Progress & Submitted Publications

- [2023] W. T. Lunardi, S. Shrestha, and M. L. Andreoni, "Hierarchical Contrastive Learning of Time Series for Out-of-Distribution Detection with Outlier Exposure," 2023, Work in progress.
- [2023] M. Gallacher, W. T. Lunardi, C. A. Boano, et al., "Out-of-Set Speaker Identification on Resource-Constrained Embedded Systems," 2023, Work in progress.
- [2023] A. S. Ali, G. Singh, W. T. Lunardi, et al., "RF Jamming Dataset: A Wireless Spectral Scan Approach for Malicious Interference Detection," *IEEE Communications Magazine*, 2023, Submitted for publication.